Guide to the Adee Dodge Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Adee Dodge papers
1930-2005
WA MSS S-2701
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
22.18
(63 boxes) + 1 broadside folder
The Adee Dodge Papers consist of drawings, research files, financial records, correspondence, and biographical files documenting the life and work of Navajo visual artist and linguist Adee Dodge. Personal papers consist chiefly of biographical documentation compiled by Dodge's daughter, Nanabah Grogan. Business papers document Dodge's uranium prospecting business in the 1950s. Research files document Dodge's research on the Navajo language and on the comparative mythology of peoples of the Native Southwest and other world cultures, including Europe and India. Also included is a transcript of the autobiography of Alex Charging Crow (also known as Alex Adams) in Lakota and in English. The custodial history of this autobiography, and Dodge's relationship to it, are undetermined. Artwork consists chiefly of sketches by Dodge, some of which are drafts of paintings. Photographs document Dodge's life and family, the landscape and people of the Navajo Nation, and Dodge's paintings. Other material includes realia (two wool rugs and art supplies).
Dodge, Adee
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Silver Wolf Books on the Frederick W. and Carrie S. Beinecke Fund for Western Americana, 2005.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Box 5 (audio cassettes): Access to original audio tapes is restricted. Reference copy may be requested. Contact Access Services for further information.
Box 63 (acetate audiodisc): Restricted fragile material. Reference copy may be requested. Contact Access Services for further information.
Arrangement
Organized into five series: I. Personal Papers and Business Papers, 1935-2005. II. Artwork, circa 1950-1973. III. Research Files, 1930-circa 1999. IV. Photographs, circa 1930-1992. V. Realia, undated.
Adee Dodge (1912-1992)
Adee Dodge, Navajo artist and linguist, was born Adolph Dodge Bitanny on November 16, 1912 in Fort Defiance, Arizona and died January 4, 1992 in Santa Fe, New Mexico. He served in the National Guard and the Army Air Corps from 1931 to 1947, achieving the rank of Captain. He studied Navajo orthography and linguistics at the Hogan School in 1934, under the guidance of Gladys Reichard. He briefly studied Anthropology at Columbia University, where he collaborated with Reichard as a linguistic consultant. In the 1930s and 1940s he worked chiefly as a Navajo language teacher and translator and contributed to a Navajo medical dictionary. In the 1950s he forayed into uranium mining, founding Adee Dodge Enterprises, Inc. His prolific career as a visual artist, begun circa 1945, flourished in his later years, when he met with commercial success.
Dodge married Effie Jean Casey in 1943, and married Veah (Mauscha M.) Pillsbury in 1950. He had one daughter, Nanabah Grogan.
Scope and Contents
The Adee Dodge Papers consist of drawings, research files, financial records, correspondence, and biographical files documenting the life and work of Navajo visual artist and linguist Adee Dodge. Personal papers consist chiefly of biographical documentation compiled by Dodge's daughter, Nanabah Grogan. Business papers document Dodge's uranium prospecting business in the 1950s. Research files document Dodge's research on the Navajo language and on the comparative mythology of peoples of the Native Southwest and other world cultures, including Europe and India. Also included is a transcript of the autobiography of Alex Charging Crow (also known as Alex Adams) in Lakota and in English. The custodial history of this autobiography, and Dodge's relationship to it, are undetermined. Artwork consists chiefly of sketches, some of which are drafts of paintings. Photographs document Dodge's life and family, the landscape and people of the Navajo Nation, and Dodge's paintings. Other material includes realia (two wool rugs and art supplies).
Art, American -- 20th Century; Artists -- United States; Artists, American; Dakota language -- Texts; Lakota dialect -- Texts; Linguists -- United States; Navajo art; Navajo artists; Navajo Indians -- Education; Navajo Indians -- Folklore; Navajo Indians -- Pictorial works; Navajo Indians in art; Navajo language -- Grammar; Navajo painting; Navajo rugs; Uranium industry -- United States; Navajo Nation, Arizona, New Mexico & Utah -- Pictorial works; Audiovisual materials; Drawings (visual works) -- United States -- 20th Century; Paintings (visual works) -- United States -- 20th Century; Photographic prints -- United States -- 20th Century; Rugs (textiles) -- United States -- 20th Century; Sound recordings; Artists -- United States -- 20th Century; Linguists -- United States -- 20th Century; Native American literature; Charging Crow, Alex; Dodge, Adee
- Personal Papers and Business Papers, 1935-2005; Series I; 1.67; (5 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Not arranged in any particular order.
  Scope and Contents
  Series I consists of biographical files, correspondence, and legal and financial documents. Personal papers consist chiefly of biographical documentation compiled by Dodge's daughter, Nanabah Grogan. Business papers document Dodge's uranium prospecting business in the 1950s.
  - Biographical files, including obituaries, 1948-1992, undated (Box 1, Folder 1-3)
  - Cards from Veah (wife), 1973, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, incoming, 1938-1957 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Adee Dodge Enterprises, Inc., 1952-1955, undated (Box 1, Folder 6-15)
    Includes articles of incorporation, clippings, maps, and material related to uranium prospecting.
  - Adee Dodge Enterprises, Inc. (continued), 1952-1955, undated (Box 2, Folder 16-18)
  - Veterans Affairs correspondence and records, 1988-1994 (Box 2, Folder 19-22)
  - Material from scrapbooks, 1935-2004 (Box 3, Folder 23-26)
    Includes biographical notes by Dodge's daughter, personal documents, correspondence, and ephemera.
  - Biographical research files compiled by Nanabah Grogan, 1950s-1990s (Box 4, Folder 27-28)
  - Interview with Nanabah Grogan, 2005 (Box 5, Folder 29)
    General note
    4 audio mini-cassettes
    Conditions Governing Access
    Access to original audio tapes is restricted. Reference copies may be requested. Contact Access Services for further information.
  - Ephemera and notes by Adee and Veah Dodge, 1955-1963, undated (Box 5, Folder 30)
  - Mirage, University of New Mexico Yearbook, 1936 (Box 5, Folder 31)
  - Mirage, University of New Mexico Yearbook, 1950 (Box 5, Folder 32)
  - Song by Veah to Tom Pillsbury, undated
    1 8-inch acetate audiodisc
    Access to original audiodisc is restricted. Reference copy may be requested. Contact Access Services for further information.
- Artwork, circa 1950-1973; Series II; 7.13; (25 boxes) + 1 broadside folder
  Organized into three subseries: Papers Relating to Artwork, Drawings and Sketches, and Other Artwork.
  Series II consists chiefly of sketches by Adee Dodge and records relating to the sale of his artwork. Also included are several paintings.
  - Papers Relating to Artwork
    - Buyer records, 1962-1973, undated (Box 6, Folder 33-38)
    - Clippings relating to Adee Dodge and his work, 1950s-1960s (Box 6, Folder 39-42)
    - Arizona Highways, printed versions, 1958-1967 (Box 6, Folder 43-44)
    - Arizona Highways, printed versions (continued), 1958-1967 (Box 7, Folder 45-46)
    - Descriptions and interpretations of Dodge paintings, by Dodge and others, undated (Box 7, Folder 47-57)
    - Photocopies of magazine covers, undated
    - "So proud the blue stallion," cover for Arizona Highways, 1959
  - Drawings and Sketches
    - Photocopies of sketches
      - 1-965, undated (Box 8, Folder 58-68)
      - 966-1046, undated (Box 9, Folder 69-70)
      - [Unidentified], undated (Box 9, Folder 71)
    - "Computer copies" of sketches, undated (Box 9, Folder 72-73)
    - Drawings (photocopies)
      - Files 153-160, undated (Box 9, Folder 74-76)
      - Unnumbered files, undated (Box 10, Folder 77-78)
    - "The Coyote", undated (Box 10, Folder 79)
    - "Turquoise Horse of the Moon Goddess", undated (Box 10, Folder 80)
    - Clippings and photographs, undated (Box 10, Folder 81)
    - Sketches, undated (Box 10, Folder 82-88)
    - Sketches, undated (Box 11, Folder 89-94)
    - Sketches and notes, undated (Box 12, Folder 95-100)
    - Sketches and notes, undated (Box 13, Folder 101-107)
    - Sketches and notes, undated (Box 14, Folder 108-115)
    - Sketches and notes, undated (Box 15, Folder 116-133)
    - Sketches, undated (Box 16, Folder 134-139)
    - Sketches, undated (Box 17, Folder 140-145)
    - Sketches, undated (Box 18, Folder 146)
    - Calendar, undated (Box 18, Folder 147)
    - Photocopies of sketches, undated (Box 18, Folder 148-150)
    - Notes, undated (Box 18, Folder 151)
    - Sketches, undated (Box 19, Folder 152-173)
    - Sketches, undated (Box 20, Folder 174-184)
    - Sketches, undated (Box 21, Folder 185-209)
    - Sketches, undated (Box 22, Folder 210-216)
    - Sketches, undated (Box 23, Folder 217-223)
    - Sketches, undated (Box 24, Folder 224)
    - Sketches, undated (Box 25, Folder 225-239)
    - Sketches, undated (Box BSD, folder 240)
  - Other Artwork
    - Paintings on board, undated (Box 26, Folder 241-242)
    - Watercolor painting of a buffalo, undated (Box 27, Folder 243)
    - Framed paintings, 1967, 1971 (Box 28, Folder 244-245)
    - Sand painting, undated (Box 29, Folder 246)
- Research Files, 1930-circa 1999; Series III; 6.17; (11 boxes)
  Series III consists of correspondence, notes, and clippings relating to Dodge's research on Navajo language, history, and ethnography, and on comparative Native American, European, and Asian mythology. Also included is a transcript (in Lakota) of the autobiography of Alex Charging Crow (also known as Alex Adams), and an English translation.
  - Correspondence, 1935-1960 (Box 30, Folder 247-249)
  - Gladys Reichard correspondence (photocopies of letters from the 1930s), undated (Box 30, Folder 250)
  - Notes on biology by Milton Lehr, 1935 (Box 30, Folder 251)
  - Notes on the Navajo Language
    - Ediphone Index, 1930s (Box 30, Folder 252)
    - [Transcriptions of audio recordings?], undated (Box 30, Folder 253)
    - Analysis of verbs (files no. 1-32, 40, 42), 1930s (Box 30, Folder 254-257)
    - Analysis of verbs (files no. 44-49, 50-58), 1930s (Box 31, Folder 258)
    - Verb stems, undated (Box 31, Folder 259-260)
    - Adjectives, undated (Box 31, Folder 261)
    - Analysis of verbs and prefixes, undated (Box 31, Folder 262)
    - List of Navajo prefixes by Edward Sapir, typescript, 1930 (Box 31, Folder 263)
    - Material related to teaching Navajo language, 1936-1941 (Box 31, Folder 264-267)
    - Translations of religious phrases into Navajo, 1978 (Box 31, Folder 268)
    - Slip files on Navajo vocabulary, undated (Box 32)
    - Slip files on Navajo vocabulary, undated (Box 33)
  - Notes on introductory Anthropology courses at Columbia, circa 1935 (Box 34, Folder 269-270)
  - Notes on Evolution and Anthropology, undated (Box 34, Folder 271-273)
  - Your Health, National Broadcasting Corporation, transcripts, 1938 (Box 34, Folder 274-276)
  - Notebooks, 1950s, undated (Box 34, Folder 277-280)
  - Notebooks, 1950s, undated (Box 35, Folder 281-293)
  - Notebooks, 1950s, undated (Box 36, Folder 294-303)
  - Material from a Criminology course, 1959 (Box 36, Folder 304)
  - "Adee Dodge, Navajo Painter," term paper by Sue Katterjohn, typescript, 1963 (Box 36, Folder 305)
  - Notes on mythology, undated (Box 37, Folder 306-315)
  - Report of the Arizona Governor's conference on the problems of the Navajo people, undated (Box 37, Folder 316)
  - Drafts of writings on Navajo culture, undated (Box 38, Folder 317-321)
  - Newspaper clippings on archaeology, and on Southwestern culture and history, 1954-1958 (Box 38, Folder 322-323)
  - Newspaper clippings on Navajo culture and military service, 1990s (Box 39, Folder 324)
  - "History of the Lakotas as told by Alex Charging Crow," Lakota version, typescript, undated [1930s?] (Box 40, Folder 325-328)
    Includes "Story of Mrs. Rump Bone."
  - "History of the Lakotas as told by Alex Charging Crow," English version, manuscript and typescript, undated [1930s?] (Box 40, Folder 329-332)
- Photographs, circa 1930-1992; Series IV; 6.92; (17 boxes)
  Organized into five subseries: Adee Dodge and Family, Adee Dodge Paintings, Events, Landscape, and Other Photographs.
  Series IV consists of photographs of Adee Dodge and family, of Dodge's paintings, and of the people and landscape of the Navajo Nation.
  - Adee Dodge and Family
    - Adee Dodge and family, 1930s-1940s, undated (Box 41, Folder 333-340)
    - Dr. Hooper's office, 1975 (Box 41, Folder 341)
    - Adee Dodge, 1940s (Box 41, Folder 342)
    - Council meetings, Henry Chee Dodge as chairman of Navajo tribe, undated (Box 41, Folder 343)
    - Medicine man from Wheatfield, undated (Box 41, Folder 344)
    - Dodge and Henry Gatewood, Window Rock, Arkansas, 1940s (Box 41, Folder 345)
    - Weavers who worked with Reichard and Bitanny; Navajo camp near Wheatfield Lake, undated (Box 41, Folder 346)
    - Navajo language class; Adults language class; Adults in hogan; Dodge-Grogan collection, undated (Box 41, Folder 347)
    - Tingly Hospital and Paul Chee Mrs. Dodge, Nanabah, undated (Box 41, Folder 348)
    - Thomas Giles Pillsbury and Meecha Pillsbury, undated (Box 41, Folder 349)
    - Dodge with wife and daughter, 1955 (Box 41, Folder 350)
    - Roger Davis and Grace family, undated (Box 41, Folder 351)
    - White Clay and Chaba's oldest sister, undated (Box 41, Folder 352)
    - Navajo family near their hogan, undated (Box 41, Folder 353)
    - Sugar Bowl Ice Cream Parlor, Nanabah C. Dodge and Veah (Meecha) Dodge, 1973 (Box 41, Folder 354)
    - Image of General MacArthur in Manila from Purple Heart Magazine, printed version, 1994 (Box 41, Folder 355)
    - Family photographs, circa 1940-1979 (Box 42, Folder 356-367)
    - Family photographs, 1980-1986 (Box 43, Folder 368-375)
    - Family photographs, 1987-1992 (Box 44, Folder 376-381)
    - Family photographs, undated (Box 45, Folder 382-388)
  - Adee Dodge Paintings
    Arranged roughly chronologically. Slides are filed at the end of the subseries.
    - Photographs of paintings, 1963-1968 (Box 46, Folder 389-396)
    - Photographs of paintings, 1969-1971 (Box 47, Folder 397-403)
    - Photographs of paintings, 1972-1974 (Box 48, Folder 404-410)
    - Photographs of paintings, 1974-1978 (Box 49, Folder 411-419)
    - Photographs of paintings, circa 1970-1983 (Box 50, Folder 420-429)
    - Photographs of paintings, undated (Box 51, Folder 430-434)
    - Slides of paintings, 1960-1968, undated (Box 52, Folder 435-444)
  - Events
    Arranged roughly chronologically.
    - Photographs of pow wows, fairs, rodeos, and other events, circa 1950-1968 (Box 53, Folder 445-452)
    - Photographs of pow wows, fairs, rodeos, and other events, 1969-1983, undated (Box 54, Folder 453-462)
  - Landscape
    - Photographs of the Navajo Nation landscape, 1967-1989, undated (Box 55, Folder 463-472)
  - Other Photographs
    - Unsorted and unidentified photographs, 1968-1991, undated (Box 56, Folder 473-482)
- Realia, undated; Series V; 1.75; (5 boxes)
  Series V. consists of art supplies and two wool rugs.
  - Rug, wool, undated (Box 57)
  - Rug, wool, undated (Box 58)
  - Colored pencils, undated (Box 59)
  - Paintbrushes, undated (Box 60)
  - Paints, undated (Box 61)
- Oversize Material, 0.25; (1 box)
  - Photocopies of magazine covers (Series II), undated (Box 62, Folder 483)
  - "So proud the blue stallion," cover for Arizona Highways (Series II), 1959 (Box 62, Folder 484)
  - Family photographs by Adee Dodge (Series IV), undated (Box 62, Folder 485)
  - Adee Dodge (Series IV), 1970s (Box 62, Folder 486)
  - Adee Dodge and family (Series IV), 1950s (Box 62, Folder 487)
  - Navajo Medical Interpreters School (Series IV), 1940 (Box 62, Folder 488-491)
- Restricted Fragile Material, 0.21; (1 box)
  - Box 5 (Box 63, Folder 492)
    Box 63 (acetate audiodisc): Restricted fragile material. Reference copy may be requested. Contact Access Services for further information.